Oh, so we haven't even started.
>> Alrighty. No. We didn't start the meeting yet. Alright. So let's Let's start out the big dog, Jeff. We know gotta wait for you. Adrian,
>> I thought you got to it, my friend. Thought you No, just trying to clear up some stuff so it'd go quicker. All right. So we're going to call
to order our Monday, January 31 Board of Selective Meeting.
It is a special budget
meeting workshop.
We're going to start with the Pledge of Allegiance.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of The United States Of America and to the Republic for which it stands
for one nation under
>> God, indivisible,
liberty, justice,
quarrel.
Okay, we're going go through public speak.
Diane Schuquette.
I'm all set, thanks. All right, Joanne Eber.
Set as well, thank you. All right, thank you very much.
We're gonna get started.
Before we get started,
I just want, because I know this is being recorded,
Eric Anderson, our town administrator,
as members of the board know,
is missing from this meeting. He was injured on a trip. We're waiting for details related to that, but he will not be joining us tonight. We all wish him well,
and
I know that he is supposed to be back in town today. So hopefully tomorrow we'll get a little bit more
information as to where he is, and we'll go from here. So
let's get started with the budget workshop.
As I had talked to Sherri and invited Jay Tuttle, Public Works Director to the meeting, I figured we could start with that area of the budget and try to go through public works, ask Jay any questions, and move forward with that area. It's the most significant part of the
operational budget for the town.
So if we can get started, we will. Jay, if you'd like to have the floor and talk to us about where you're looking to take public works, we'd greatly appreciate it.
>> Good evening, everybody.
Any particular you want to start with? Just want me to go over each budget?
There's
several parts, so the operating capital
building.
>> Well,
let's start with your,
unless anybody has any problems, your capital requests, and We can sit there and that'll give us some guidance as to what you're thinking about for the department.
>> On
the
capital side of things,
some of which
such as the
bridges and culverts and those things,
don't have a lot to do with Eric has that and some of that is
ongoing,
continue continuing
work.
The connectivity grant,
you know, the sidewalks that are going down Long Hill and connected to the
library and whatnot. That's
I haven't really had much to do with that, so I won't Okay. Speak to that. To the equipment. Okay.
So on the roads you're looking for. So
we're looking to try to do approximately
8.6
miles this year, consisting of Bear Swamp, Wheeling,
Skinner, Long Hill,
portion of Long Hill that's not gonna be part of the
construction work that's been planned for a couple of years now.
So it's from
Bear Swamp on to Skinner, that section along Hill. Hendy Road, Old Farm, Shad Blow, Dogwood, Wood Fern. Go slower.
I'm
>> sorry. Is
that somewhere that I'm missing that details?
Just wanted to write the roads down.
8.6
miles to
do preservation.
Yep. Bear Swamp, Skinner. Bear Swamp,
>> Wheeling,
Skinner Hill,
Yeah. And we're looking to work with Coventry to include their sections.
They pay for their portion.
Long Hill Road, the section
from Bear Swamp to Skinner.
Hendy,
Old Farms,
Shadlow,
Dogwood,
Wood Fern.
>> So you're staying on that side of town? Yes. So
>> that would basically
we're looking to do the same
preservation
as what we did last year. Shim,
where we paid the
bad sections,
get everything into shape,
chip seal,
and any striping on the main roads that we need to do.
And prior
to that we'll do some crack sealant in those areas too on the major
areas where we could do some crack seal.
So we figured that the,
cost of that
would be let me hang on, I got a lot of notes here.
It's about $48,000
per mile.
Hang on here.
Operating budgets.
How much did you say per mile, Jay? 48,000?
>> Yeah, it's about 40 well, we spent about 48,000
per mile last year.
So that's $412,800.
Yeah.
>> And where is that, Sherry, on our list on our
spreadsheet?
Jay,
that's just not supplies. I mean,
you're figuring $48,000
and that includes labor. What are you doing with it? Yeah, includes
our paving,
the asphalt,
the contractor,
chip seal.
Yeah.
>> So it's all out of pocket expenses or, you know, outside contractor expenses. Yeah.
>> Okay. Yeah. So we're, we're, I
believe,
and Sherry, you're going to have to help me out on this, are starting
what we have balance
between TAR and
Capitol Roads is
at like 94,000,
95,000
in tar.
You're on mute.
Cherry, you're muted.
There you go. $92,800.18
is in Qatar on
2122.
The Capital Roads?
>> And the
road improvement fund. Is that the one you want? Or?
Yeah. Yeah.
$166,654.10.
2122.
Alright. I have tree removal
fund
$19,295
I am Bunker Hill Bridge Fund,
$278,096.31.
Bridge and Culvert,
$127,047.72.
Building maintenance fund is 87,381.81.
So we have go approx
ahead. The figures I gave you. Yeah. Going over.
>> So we have approximately $258,000
to get started on roadwork prior to
prior to our fiscal year.
>> Well,
have
you have you so okay.
And we're budgeting. It looks like we're budgeting next year. We're looking the department request was $330,000
in your road improvement fund?
>> Correct.
And when I totaled up,
when I totaled up the
road miles,
and
some of this is going to be,
well, it's a very small portion of Coventry we'll be paying for, so it won't make. So
originally we thought it'd be somewhere just a little over seven miles when Eric and I talked about it, And when I totaled up the actual road miles, it's 8.6.
So I think we're closer to the, if we're going to try to do everything that's on this list is $400,000
in that neighborhood.
>> Well, you've got road improvement road improvement plus tar, so you should be within shooting distance of that. Yeah.
>> Yep.
Well,
I look I've I've been looking at it and it's part of my mental block is tar and capital, same, same bucket.
>> Well, you've got about, I mean, from my recollection,
you should have about 94,000,
95,000
of yearly expenses that are not straight road. Yep. So,
well, they are road, but it's guardrail replacement,
signage,
whatever, whatever that ends up ending up in tar.
And then you've got the balance end up going into roadwork. So,
that should give or take,
that should give or take get you to 400 ks.
Correct. And you have how much?
Totally Right
now?
>> Your total ex no, your total expenses that you need. Yep.
For your stuff that you want to do is how much? 4?
It's about 412,000.
>> So you're really close with what you're asking in total. Yeah, And depending on how the
>> different bids come in and what we go with,
you know, the cost of
the different, you know, the catch basin cleaning, you talked about the
guardrail replacement, things like that. So if we have to
remove a road when I get into the preservation, if we go over on pavement on asphalt,
I may have to cut back on one of the roads that need to be chip sealed to cover that.
And we did that a little bit last year.
>> We're hoping So are we doing recover? So we're doing,
we're doing those types of roads in the front end so that we know if we need to cut back chip sealing
on the back end? Correct.
Schedule wise. Okay. Yep.
Yep.
>> You said you were not dealing with bridging culvert, really?
No. I haven't been.
>> K.
Now you have a treatment We haven't we haven't well, we haven't really
>> we haven't really been doing anything other than,
you know, the repairs to Bunker Hill. I've been keeping
track of those,
>> any expenses obviously. That's fine. We,
we get that you haven't had time to get there. We, you got a small staff, but. Skipping
that and going to tree removal
fund, you're asking for 75 this year, 25,000 more.
Yes.
>> Is there? I mean, we did a ton this past year. What do we got left?
>> We got a, right now we have approximately,
I believe $18,000
left
in
the budget.
>> Roads are you looking at when you talk about that $75,000
What do we have left to do or what are priorities for that 75,000?
>> Well,
right now it's in that's the same general area.
First, first and foremost on the list is Gilead. We've got a lot of work that needs to be done on Gilead.
You got a couple of big ones.
>> We look to do the tree removals
or tree work,
we're hoping that we
coincide that with the road work so we get the
most
try to get as much work on those roads prior to the actual work, you know, so tree removal so we don't have to go back on them with that equipment right away.
The big equipment? The yes.
>> So Yeah. That's total available for tree work, 93,000?
Yep.
What did we spend last year, Jay? You remember?
>> Well,
we we were upwards of 50.
It was a little over 50, I believe. I think we started with 50.
>> Yeah. We started with 50 and then we we pulled money from other places.
>> Right. And then we had that we were able to do that co op with Eversource,
which
gave us a lot more
value for our dollar. Thanks
for our buck.
Are we doing that again?
>> Oh, yes. We're gonna try to continue to do that as long as they're receptive to it and willing,
we hope to continue that.
We should,
absolutely.
>> Oh yeah, yeah. I've been trying to get ahold of them recently just because we while there's,
Distinctive is out there in that area right now, we're we're kinda hoping we could get Gilead done while while they're out that way.
But I haven't been able to lock that up yet.
>> Any more work need to be done on Boston Hill Road?
That state?
No. Just a joke. I'm sorry. Yeah.
Don't worry. I'll put in a list for you.
My best friend in town.
>> Complaining. I I hear I hear Oak Farms is getting personal attention too.
Yeah. Oh, really? That's interesting.
Okay. Extension,
I think, we call that.
>> Jay, just so I get it, we have $588,000
in potential
funds available for road work,
and you had $412,000
of
miles that you would like to do
based upon where you're at. So that
leaves $176,000
Adrian, you were sitting there saying that's other miscellaneous roadwork that
potentially could be required or what
are we doing there?
I'm sorry, repeat the question.
>> So in totality, the TAR money available and
well,
we got to remember that TAR is going to be replenished.
What's the replenishment on TAR expected for next year?
Next year?
>> They've
been pretty steady on that over the years, and it's somewhere around $93.94.
Yeah. I was going to say that in
>> two drops. We have another payment coming in for that, around that month. So you're getting 180 ish? 180 in total. Yeah. But, but the problem is about one of those goes to regular maintenance services. So it goes to guardrails,
it goes to, you know,
basin cleaning,
all the other things that we do in town that aren't necessarily rebuilding rooms, but are just general maintenance of them. Okay.
>> Then the math, Adrian, really works. It was 94,000
available
in TAR money. That's what we'd have.
We got 166
that's left in Townhade Road.
That's
$2.58. We were budgeting $3.30.
That gets you to $5.88 and Jay recommended
$412,000
of roadwork.
We have some extra money there.
>> I was doing the math for residents so that when they ask why we get 150 in tar or 190 in tar and we don't spend it all on roads, we do. It's just not, we have to budget some for
basic cleaning and, you know, the new signage around the lake, all those types of things fall into that that second bucket. That's all.
Right.
>> The other thing to consider when when you're putting all the
adding all the math up is the
balance that you have at the end of the construction season. So basically
the the 94,000
or 92,000
in that $1.66
is
basically
leftover from last year, which it is,
but it gives us
money
to start Starting money. Yeah. Yep. So we can get started right away in the construction season and we're the first in line to get the contractors.
And then we have the bulk of our
preservation
done
in the summertime and not early
fall or
God forbid late fall. So it's,
and that way
we have money hopefully left over again for the following year.
Yep.
>> Okay.
So just on that note, like what contracts do we have lined up to move forward in June,
July? What do we have?
>> Well,
right now
I don't have any
signed,
but we're working on the catch base and getting in the bids for that.
Waiting for the obviously the asphalt I try to, I try to keep in mind I budget for a thousand ton of asphalt.
Asphalt's gonna run probably I'm guessing
$80
ish a ton, hopefully a little bit less. Last year we got a pretty good deal, so I don't know, might be $75 $76 a ton, but I figure $80 a ton for a budget figure.
And
hopefully I don't, depending on the needs, we don't go over on that.
The paving contractor
is
around the $90,000
mark.
So,
yeah,
gypsia, that's
gonna be depending and it'll probably run, I'm guessing around $2.80
to 300 in that range.
>> Jay, just for everyone's edification, are we using state bid and
then going
from there? Or are we doing RFPs for this stuff?
>> We're running state, we use state bid pricing and also there's Croc.
So the two
companies that are, we'll call them qualifying for Andover,
They both run state bid pricing and or crock.
>> Do we talk to both of them and are we splitting work between them or how are we doing it at this point?
For the chip seal? No, you said you have two qualified companies. So how are we deciding who does the work? Oh, well, it's just two companies that we've used in the past
that are able to do the chip seal.
>> Okay.
And what about paving? How are we making that decision? The asphalt
>> that's
by Crocbid and
that's the closest asphalt plant for us is AEN
out of Franklin.
And then
the paving contractor that we use,
we do that by
bits from different
paving companies. And we try to get we try to find a paving company that will do a day price. They have all the equipment
that's needed
other than just paving because sometimes they need a little bit of construction equipment too. Okay. So we're doing day rates basically? Yes. Okay. Perfect.
>> Jay, just for one other thing, I know it's a grant, but where are we at with the work that's going to be done on Shawnee Mill?
>> Hoping that we're gonna get started back on Shawty
as soon as the weather breaks. If
March is a good month, we'll get started.
We have drainage work to get done there, and then we have a
little bit of work on Long Hill prior to
reclamation and pavement.
We'll try to plan, we'll try to plan that out.
So the pavement can be done
early fall, late summer, early fall on that.
>> Okay.
So what happened this year so we can understand a little bit and maybe that'll lead us into the other part of the conversation.
Is it, is it, it seemed like you guys were ready to go on shotty and then all of a sudden you weren't there for a month and a half. Is that the bridge situation?
>> No, it was. It was the well,
led into that prop, was part of that problem, but we all that storm,
damage that came up with the erosion on the sides of the roads,
We spent the better,
oh, the better part of three weeks
on just
redoing the erosion on the roads, the edges of the roads,
filling those back in,
reseating,
getting the get it stabilized.
>> And then then we ended up having to do the repairs on Bunker Hill Bridge. So so residents may not have understood what was going on there because they didn't see damage to the road itself. What exactly do you mean when you say
filling in and all that so people can understand what you were doing?
>> As far as the edges of the road, the water coming down, like specifically,
well, Hendy, Skinner, we had a lot of damage over there.
You know, if you go down the side, as you're traveling down the sides of the road and,
you know, you see
the edges of the road gone,
>> Pavement- What does that mean? Why is that a problem? What's it doing?
>> Well, if you drive off the edge of the road,
you're at, you know, end up getting stuck on the side of the road or take out the bottom of your car.
Those
are our watercourses.
Try to get the
wherever our watercourses watershed to get off to the road. So if it's being caught on the side of the road and not allowed to get off the road in certain spots
In the past,
you get a little something in different areas.
A quick fix is throw a little gravel in there with no organic
material to grow grass or something to stabilize the edge of that road. So those are prone areas that wash out right away.
So this time,
because we had so much of it,
we mixed up our own material combination
of loam and stone.
So if you had a six, eight inch, some places were a foot deep,
some even more.
We were putting in organic matter and then seeding it so it would grow grass right away to stabilize that side of the road. So if somebody wants to or has to pull off the side of the road for whatever,
they're not falling into some ditch.
>> And so that that keeps the water from getting underneath the road too. Is that right? Yeah.
>> We want it to keep it from getting off, underneath the road and we want the water to get off the road. So we're establishing
those waterways
and if you've seen us out there anywhere,
especially this
fall where we're scraping the edges of the road, getting the leaves off the road, So we we don't want water to stay on our road edges. Want we want to try to get the road off into our ditches
and water courses where the watershed needs to go.
Okay. And some areas
where it did get undermined,
GeraVati is a good
comes to mind and by the ledges there.
We cut that
road out a little bit right along the ledges,
filled it in, and then we had to repave it. So we and we paved it right into the ledge rather than leaving an area that was exposed
>> that was prone to washing out. So so we so you were running around putting out fire. So it wasn't just the bridge. It was the bridge and and some water damage and some other things. Oh yeah.
A lot. It was a lot of stuff going on. Is that a normal course of business or is this an unusual year to have?
Is that kind of how it happens?
>> Yeah. It it's, it's just, it it's hit or miss. Some years you have a it's not too bad, but other times
somebody goes
they get on the side of the road in the soft spot, soft ditch, and they cause a wheel rut. That's a place for water to go. Sits there and it's soft and it erodes.
And later on, we may have to go fix that.
We just every time we find a spot, we try to make it better than what it was. Okay.
>> Okay. So the request,
just so I get it, is $330,000
for
road improvement fund and
$75,000
for the tree
removal fund.
So road improvement fund, tree removal fund.
Okay?
Anyone have any more questions related to
the work that Jay's proposing?
>> I'm good on work. Would like to understand how
he would
work in the extra guy and the summer guy. I know Scott had some questions about last time when we were discussing this. Scott, do you want to take the lead on that or? I'm just yeah, I'm just curious if there's
gonna be enough work for an extra
two people.
Let's go to those sections.
Okay.
That's section 300.
>> And did we get the numbers
in here to see what that looks like?
Sherry, did those numbers get updated?
Sherry, you're muted.
>> I'm
hoping I don't have to talk too much. That's what it is because I have an abscess too.
When
I looked at it,
there were
it was already put in the
budget
spreadsheet.
And the only thing that wasn't put in there
was
the fifth full time person at Public Works.
So
the budget includes the promotion,
RB from maintainer one to two,
increase
in
Jay's salary, and a part time summer helper
is already included in there.
>> Well, did the you did all the salary increases, so the contractuals for the union too, right? Mhmm. Absolutely.
When we look What's at
>> not there, excuse me one second, is that fifth full time
person at Public Works?
That's
what's missing.
That is not in there.
Oh, you didn't put that up. Okay.
>> No. Do you have a did you? I just opened we discuss it tonight and I get
more
information.
Yeah, we have had that last week.
>> No, but we did ask. I was hoping that you have a general number so we can punch in if we want to.
Entry level employee with
benefits?
>> I don't have the contract in front of me right now. So Okay. I can get that number for you, though.
Alright.
>> So Scott, you were asking is how does that fifth person plan?
>> Great, we're gonna be we're gonna have
another
team of people because we're gonna have one guy who's gonna be taking
one person's
most of his summer work we're gonna get with the seasonal guy and the other guy they're gonna add a new guy and we're gonna have another team
of people, which is good. I'm just making sure that we have enough work for
another team of men.
>> Jay, can you address that? What, how you would, how you break
up the work assignments and how that would play out?
>> So as I understand it,
when Eric and I first put this together, okay, so the,
if we add on,
a temp, full time temp
that would give two guys
and just throw it for, you know, roadside mowing. Okay. One guy's roadside mowing. We have an operator now.
It give, that person
not only do they,
they can ride behind in safety situations
where,
you know, for traffic control,
but that person can park the truck
while they're,
behind and they can do weed whacking, they can do trimming around the signs, they can do even do small
tree trimming if there's some low branches along the way. If there's a stretch of time where he's not needed
for for that, say the roadside mowers and there's a lot of places where the he can be out by themselves, we can utilize that person in other areas of our construction work,
labor and then for
such as drainage work, whatnot. Now, go ahead. Currently,
>> when those guys are in an unsafe area, as you put it, you're pulling somebody else to go to go be behind them with traffic or something? Yeah.
>> Yeah. So right now we got take
me out of the equation. I'm a I'm a fourth. I'm the fourth
crew,
you know, right now I'm
doing the admin
running, you know, taking care of stuff here in the office, and I do
the little jobs, the one man
things. I can bounce around, I can if you need a little traffic control, I can go help you out. If I gotta go
fill up one, a couple of potholes, I can go fill a couple of potholes. If we got a whole bunch of potholes, well then it's two guys.
So I do the little things.
So you got one guy that's primarily roadside mowing
pretty much all year long.
There's
part of the time. Well, except right now he's out in a plow truck.
Not today. Not right this minute. But, you
know, that's that's a full time position right there.
So the other two guys currently,
they're doing all the other when
we had to do the road edges, the erosion.
So they're out doing doing that. They're doing the construction,
the drainage project over there on Shottie Mill Road. Their primary is two guys over there. When you get into the drainage work,
many times two guys is that's where we're lacking in help
is we don't have enough people
for drainage work doing that kind of thing. That's where you need that third guy.
You need somebody in a truck, need somebody in a machine, you need somebody in the hall.
And if
the truck isn't
needed right away during a stretch, you got two guys to get somebody's
building a catch basin and
they're laying pipe together, putting stone in the trench. You know, it's it's all hands on deck when we're doing drainage work. And many right now, many times the roadside mowing gets put off when we're doing drainage work. We, you know, we have everybody on that
work that job.
>> Okay. I think that's
not what
we assumed. I thought that
that one guy was going to be seasonal work
and you know additional help if there was a traffic situation
and that we are going to add another team. Is is it that what everybody else
thought?
>> I
didn't take it that way. I took it as, you know, them
really just kind of needing more help in general. And based on the diversity of assignments that they do, as Jay pointed out, sometimes you have a guy by himself.
Sometimes you have two guys together and sometimes you need more than a couple guys on a project you might when you're spreading material.
You may be doing some of it with a with a with a small loader
and then you got a couple guys raking it behind them. So you got two guys raking, you got a guy in the loader, you know, that's three guys right there, you know. So You know, Bunker
>> Hill Road was another one of our roads that eroded real bad
and
two guys were spreading material
and I was in the pickup truck
rolling,
you know, they were putting a little windrow right in the, in those eroded areas,
and I was using the pickup truck,
rolling the material in, kind of giving it some compaction,
then I would pull over, get out of the way, and I would rake it, and then we were all teaming up and throwing grass seed down. So,
and, you know, just trying to keep up. So,
we
help each other out. There isn't
there's
you know, when you get into the construction
side of things, a two man crew
doesn't really cut it. It can we can do it, but it's really slow.
Having a three man crew, somebody goes out on vacation or needs a day off
No. Then now the job sits.
>> And and we don't we don't allow them
don't currently, we don't currently allow them to take winter vacation because we need everybody for plowing.
So we have to let them take it during the summer, even though that's our busiest season for construction.
>> Yeah.
Yeah.
So we we work it out
currently.
I mean, do the best we can,
but
we, you know, we're limited.
We're limited in in how fast we can get a job done. And if something happens, we get a storm.
We had, you know, a couple of tree storms too last year that put us know, we had to go around and clean
up a lot of tree debris.
So that that was an added couple of weeks there,
just getting that work done.
>> So just so I understand it and to to deal with this, is is you're looking to have
a seasonal
employee
that
would work with,
let's say, the individual that would do all of the mowing. So you're really saying, I'm going to keep a
crew on to mow and maintain
the town, then you're going use three guys to sit there and do all of your construction work. So there's going be a three man crew
to do construction work, and then there's going to be a two man crew to do
mowing and town maintenance.
>> Yes, and then the two can help each other out. You know, if we have
>> trees stuff, know, tree, a storm got a lot of trees clean up, we go help the other crew. Well, you also you have we have traffic control to that we have to provide for certain jobs. So you may pull the second man from the
from the weed whacking crew or the mowing crew for that. Yep,
>> but in essence you're always going to have one person
doing
maintenance from a mowing
perspective
>> at all times during the summer, unless someone takes a day off or somebody does something. Yeah, I mean that mowing machine is going all the time. Then, you know, we try
to play catch up this time of year.
There isn't snow on the ground and we did it right up until it snowed, you know, we were out
cutting back with the mower,
you know, doing our pushbacks because during the busy season,
during the growing season, we're lucky if we can keep up with one pass. We're lucky if we can get a second pass it just to just to stay up. We just keep things safe and keep it maintained.
>> I'm
pretty sure that that when this came to us,
it was explained to us that we were gonna have
three teams.
I'm I'm pretty certain that that's how it was explained.
And that one seasonal guy was gonna do the list of that
Eric gave us.
Was gonna be
cross trained on the big mower and he was gonna be doing all the mowing. I think that's why we wanted Jay here so Jake could explain. Yeah, I wouldn't, I
>> personally,
I wouldn't,
unless it come, the person that runs that roadside mower comes with a lot of experience,
I wouldn't be just putting anybody on a roadside mower.
That, that mowing machine,
and we had a couple, you know,
where I
forget what it was, but something broke on the some pins and bushings,
something let go on the mower and it was two or three weeks out, but
before we got it back on the road again.
Those machines
are very high maintenance
and you do the one wrong thing on that thing and that arm, yeah, it's not something you just put anybody in the machine.
I don't recommend that.
And I'm not sure where you get
three
teams or three work crews out of adding a man and a half.
I I don't see that.
>> Jay, I think we're just trying to I I think we're asking to understand. I don't think anyone's
>> trying to I'm do the math for good with it any way you do it, Jay, but that's not how it was portrayed to the board before. Maybe nobody remembers that, but Well, Scott, you're not wrong. We were always looking at
>> two person crews.
Was never explained to us a three person crew should be that crew for maintenance. We knew that people were pulled to go help you do drainage and to do other Right, right. But at least this is an understanding.
I mean, listen, if you weren't doing any road work, you could have with what you're saying in the summer, and you're going to be doing road work anyway, you could sit there and have three trucks going with two people in each truck going to do some different project.
So Scott, in essence, that's your three teams, but if you're going to sit there and look at it where you have a crew doing drainage and doing everything else, that's three people.
Then you have a full time
mower
that is experienced in the roadside mower and then you have the seasonal help
and they're going out trying to maintain
every grass area in this community.
I
have no problem with that concept.
Sherry, you need to get with Jay
and you need to give us a number that that
additional
staff person would cost so we can deal with it. Go ahead.
>> On the document that we handed out,
Eric and I worked on the recommended personnel
options under the public works,
there are
some figures there that we costed out.
The full time
maintainer one,
it was going to be $71,000
and that included single
coverage insurance.
If you had
married,
you would have to add an additional $10,100
and married with children,
you'd have to add an additional $16.06.
And those are the figures that we were working with when we prepared
this document together.
So if that's not something that
is,
you know,
we can use, then I'll go back to the contract and
>> refigure it. Nope. If you've got the numbers, I, we just want them punched in though, to the sheet. Yeah. I understand. No. I'll, I'll punch them in.
I mean, we can edit it, but we'll probably screw it up.
No, I can put him in. Then
>> just Sherri, just so we know, are you doing those changes during our meeting so that we don't miss anything? Or are you doing them I'm writing them all down. And then when I'm, I'm taking this document,
>> and tomorrow I will plug all the figures
in
for you that we've talked about.
And then I will hand you a spreadsheet.
So Can
>> I ask a question?
It possible next
budget meeting? Can we have Sherry
share her screen
and plug it in so we can see it and show it to everybody at the same time?
>> That
would be beneficial. I would request that. I would follow-up if it can, because it would be
positive, Sherry, if you've updated something and we increase something, we at least understand the total amount of the increase. So we're
>> having a real time conversation.
Now, Sherry, you had concerns that you only have the one computer.
>> I mean, can you do I that can set it up either I'll stay at work or, you know,
whatever needs to happen, I'll do it. Sherry, you need a second screen.
>> Come on. We got to go there.
You got to get a second screen. There's
got to be a screen in the office.
I'm sure.
>> Right.
So
Sherry, just so I can hear it again,
what
is
the maintainer position that we would add?
Maintainer one.
Don't go through everything. Just tell me the full boat insurance
>> as high as it could possibly go. High as it could possibly go? With insurance. How much is the down? I understand. 87,000.
87. Angels.
Calculator
here.
What about the,
seasonal guy? Yep, 87,600.
The seasonal guy was in, Scott, at
That was added. Right? That was $20,000.
$20,000
was added. Yes. $17,500
increase.
So that's 17,000 So that's already in. Yes.
The 20,000 seasonal is already in.
>> So we're talking about like a $125,000
of
increases, but it's
actually higher than that. Dollars 171,000
for that
section of public works.
It's a big number.
>> Jay, I
have a question for you Jay about how
long do you want the seasonal guy
for? I I think that like Hebron keeps theirs.
I'm pretty sure through October.
>> Yeah. Typically it's you want to be around the six months,
you know, April to September,
you know, and again, it depends, you know,
if they, if you get them out of,
if you they're getting out of college, it could be from,
you know, beginning of June. Just depends on how you have it set up.
Are we gonna But I I'm figuring at least six months.
That's what that's what my thought was when Eric and I had this discussion. And we were figuring how much the,
18 an hour, I think. Right? I thought it was 20.
>> 18, 20. The the range, it was $18
to $20
an hour.
So 19.
In that range.
>> I think Jay honestly I'd rather leave a range on it because if you get somebody that walks in that's green.
Yeah. Work the hours, then there may be at 18, but if somebody comes in and says yeah
I have experience and you take them out and you know, they can run a roadside mower or they can do something else or they have a lot of landscaping experience or you know, something else that contributes, well then maybe we're offering them 20. Yeah. Know,
this isn't a long term growth position like a union job where they have a maintainer one maintainer two etc.
So you know, I think I'd rather leave the flexibility in the number.
Agreed.
>> So you're starting in May then, the May 1? Well, it depends. We haven't had that discussion,
>> you know, are we looking to get somebody
right in May or
are we looking, you know, if it's gonna be somebody
somebody get college kid?
>> Yeah, Scott. When when are you available, Scott? That's what we need to know. When's your schedule open up? Adrian, you don't have my telephone number, okay?
I've been put on the banned list. Anyway,
>> with all these changes, our numbers
are going to go even higher than the number that we Right. Because
>> we're up to 18 if you six months for $19
an hour.
>> Well, you're never going to be able I mean, just so we all understand, we only have $2,500
in the budget. You'd have to pull it from somewhere else. We
only have $2,500
so if you wanted to start them in May, it's kind of
a question of where we're going to get those funds. I
would be okay with starting them early because
I think if you get to it and get started early you're going to be looking better at the end of the year so the sooner you get to it the better off you're going to be. Yeah mid April or something.
The problem that we face as a board is
that's going to be almost a $200,000
bump in this department.
All
necessary, but we have to sit there and really be able to support that increase,
and we have to make sure that
Adrian finds us the money somewhere else
to make this all happen.
>> I
think personally that
residents can look around and see
the amount of work that Public Works has done in the last three years between the transfer station,
the trees and the roadwork
and see that we're going in the right direction and if we're going to continue to do that
and be able to stay on top of it, this is where we need to be. Think this is the right number
and I'm hoping it'll be the right number of people and that once we get caught up with some of this other stuff, this drainage work, the more we can keep in house, the more money we save
and then once we get caught up a little bit, you know, we may be at a point where then you maybe at that point, you don't need the the extra man and through attrition whether it's
Tommy gets to the point of retirement or one of the other guys Richard or somebody.
Then maybe you don't replace that guy if you're at a point where you don't feel that you're going to continue
to have that increased drainage load,
but if you do, then you keep them, but I think this is the right time to add someone.
You know, to keep going in that direction, so you know, and the more we sub out
the more it's going to cost us so we're going to pay once or pay twice it's up to us, you know.
>> Well,
don't have any problem
Adrian, with the logic. I think Jay and his crew have done
a great job.
The town looks better than it has in a long time.
Think
>> we have done what we needed to do with our due diligence that the town can trust us enough to ask for this. That's
>> a lot to ask trust,
but yes, they should.
But I would sit there and say the one thing that is lacking
is a better job maintaining
the grass areas within our town. Think that's
the biggest lack
for public works. So Jay, just so you understand, it's not a knock, and it might be that you just don't have the staff, But that is the biggest issue for me personally as a resident is that there's areas within the town that just
need to be maintained better because as people drive through town or drive around town,
it reflects
on our community.
>> Why, that's what I was, I'm also
saying the same thing Jay and I would think that if we got two extra people, we are getting two extra people, it's only for whatever six or seven months too but you know the rest of the year it's mostly snow plowing but
we're gonna have two extra people so I would assume that every
bit of grass is gonna be cut really well so when I drive down Route 6,
I know that somebody was there and it's all done cleaned up nice.
So that's what I'm assuming.
>> So those areas
form first and foremost they need to be identified And I think we've done some of that in some of You have, those you have, and it looks nice. And
keep in mind
that
those areas
potentially could be high maintenance for the department and keeps us away from taking care of those
drainage areas
and the problem areas that are continuing,
continue to, how
can I say it,
I don't want to say haunt the town, but they're just it's it's always out there? And if we don't address them,
they don't go away.
We continually do,
are doing repairs
on,
you know, you can do a band aid in one section and you go away from it for a while, but keep in mind, you got to go back and fix it right.
If you don't fix it, putting out fires, Jay. Is that what I'm trying to say? And if you don't fix it, you're just going to keep going back again because
we don't have time to do it right. We got to go and take care of the things that
people see day in day out. And it's the things that you don't see
that are costing you the most money.
My
understanding with the grassy areas,
I know you have a contractor that's been taking care of
most of those areas
and there's some things that maybe they can't do that we do have to do, but we have to isolate those areas exactly what
we have to do so we're not spending so much time. Because a contractor,
they have manpower,
they have all the equipment,
and
they're, you know, they're doing those
areas that,
take us away from doing the important work. So I make a suggestion?
>> One of the things we did,
this had to be probably
six years ago, seven years ago.
We had a little bus tour
of certain parts of town with the border select bin. Do you remember that Jeff Babar?
I do.
Thought that
was really helpful
when I was on the board of finance to have that
little trip.
And that may be appropriate,
you know Scott and yourself,
you know getting together with Jay and talking about and maybe we all be part of that conversation, but what the priorities are exactly because.
You know, this is what is my concern this year as much as we wanted to do a bunch of the stuff down at Veterans Park you know, we took public works out of the loop for and ended up being a couple of weeks by the time it was all said and done.
We took two weeks out of their prime time schedule to have them doing stuff down at Veterans. Now, don't get me wrong, Veterans is important to me, but when we throw things like that at their schedule, we're part of the problem,
you know.
We're taking them away from a wireturn on shoddy or why aren't you here? Why aren't you there? Well, because we're asking to do other things on on a short term priority list.
We have to be part of the solution instead of part of the problem when we have that conversation.
Okay.
>> Well,
let's sit there and we'll
schedule a ride around in April.
Okay.
Sounds like a good idea.
>> But we still have the same issue that we're having to increase this budget line item $200,000
I
>> think we
put it together and
you know, and I think we asked, you know, we talked to Board of Finance and say we'd like to at least let residents have one one shot at it.
Know, for residents come back and say that that is too high, then,
then we deal with it, but I
think we got to at least take a shot at it.
>> On
the operating budget, not to change the subject, but or in within the operating budget, do you have
the
the new mower head and
conveyor assembly for the sweeper as part of the
Capital?
>> Well,
did you put it I put it in the operating site because it's basically a repair, but It is in operations. It's under vehicle
>> maintenance, actually. Correct.
So $32,000
for $20,000
for the mower head and $10,000
for
sweeper conveyor.
>> That I would prefer,
and that'll be a board of finance decision, but I think that should be moved to,
you know, a capital repair instead of an ongoing maintenance
line.
>> Well,
that would take $30,000
out of a $40,000
request. So that's fine. I do agree with you there, Adrian. I do, Adrian, also. It's a piece of
capital equipment. Equipment.
Yeah. Sherry, can you move that?
Yep.
>> Jay, I didn't see those come across CIP over there.
It's what is it? 20 and what?
>> It's
20,000 for the roadside mower head.
Mhmm.
And
10,000
for the conveyor assembly.
Okay. On the sweeper.
>> Can you
put those together for CIP please?
Oh, can I put them? Okay. Sorry. They have gone through CIP before budget, unfortunately.
>> Yeah, well,
okay.
I was told to put them under vehicle maintenance because it's kind of a repair.
>> Yeah, it's too much. It's too much money to qualify as a repair though. Okay. Well,
all right.
So you want a CIP request?
>> And one other thing,
Jay, and you're no, I'll say this to Sherry. Sherry, all of these empty rows that we've consolidated, I'm assuming that
Board of Finance Adrian has approved of all of the elimination of all of those rows.
Can we get rid of them?
>> I am not privy to the Board of Finance's decision on that.
Diane Scharquette's on the meeting if you want to ask her or Joan.
>> Diane,
can all of these rows that have zeros in them, can we get rid of them?
>> Yeah, I haven't seen the spreadsheet that you're looking at. So
if
it's part of GL numbers that we aren't going to be using anymore, have no problem getting rid of them.
We need to make sure that we have a good chart of accounts of, because I know we consolidated
multiple
items and
to one line for the new budget year this year's. I
want to make sure we can able to track what we paid last year so we can compare apples to apples.
Yeah.
>> So you want the consent you want, you want the.
So for example, in public works, there's a bunch of miscellaneous. You want everything consolidated on the, you want everything consolidated from the previous year so that you have apples to apples.
>> Or just a, just a cheat sheet to tell us that these four
buckets are now in this one bucket and the new budget that's all I need to know you know what I mean.
>> Don't know you don't read you're on the meeting to you don't recall that that you guys haven't seen the sheet yet, right? No, we have not.
>> Can you forward that to the Madrian? Like now? Yeah. Oh, I haven't seen it yet.
All right.
So, okay.
Think getting rid of those rows will
make life easier.
The only rows to get rid of are rows that don't have numbers for last year. Even if they have no numbers for this year, you keep them, but if they were zero last year and zero this year, it would help to have them
off. Okay.
>> That's interesting.
And I guess, Sherry, the one other thing is you're gonna have to I don't know how this happened, but
we had twenty twenty-twenty twenty one actual expenses and items that we didn't have an approved budget line item,
so we've got to figure that part of it out.
Okay.
>> Jay, drop down to the snow removal area
or your section snow removal.
Maybe?
Line 467.
Row 467.
>> Oh, you want me to look at something on snow removal?
I don't have any of that. I don't have any of your spreadsheets. What's that? You're fired.
Have my
spreadsheet.
>> Okay, so let's translate the items that go into 303,130.
>> Okay.
You don't do it like that?
No, I don't have your spreadsheets, I have mine. Do you have your GL account numbers associated
with your spreadsheet?
Apparently not. I haven't gotten that information.
I
number,
think
Jeff, is on his spreadsheet.
>> Hold on a second. 303 what?
130.
Okay. Yep. 130. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
It does coordinate?
It's wages.
>> Okay.
Sorry. But the numbers
coordinate
to something that you're working off of?
On
Listen, it's just OT.
I have 1500750.
Correct.
>> Diane and Joan, you should have the spreadsheets and the gram list.
>> So
that
is what's on
that row.
And then you go down and you have supplies
where you're asking.
We have a $70,000
request.
That's
On the snow budget? Yeah. $6.42.
>> Okay. Standing equipment.
So nothing is really changing in your mind from your snow
>> removal request from the prior year? No, snow, the thing, the only thing that, and I, to be honest with you, I haven't really had
the time
other than just
kind
of a standard
increase.
What
what I've been finding
in discussions with Eric,
between last year and now this year,
our overtime,
we were
probably a little short on that.
With this past storm, we're already over our overtime for this year.
It's And been pretty tight on
I'm really not sure that we're, that we've been over by that much. I think they reduced you last year. They did. It used to always be 25.
>> Well, we would, it was, it was over. Reduced by
10 last year. You're right. Well, we, so I cut it
when I was on board of finance, put in a motion to cut it, you know, a bunch of years ago because it was way over
for several years in a row but we had those light years. Do you remember we had,
you know, we had a couple years where we only had like, you know, five or six plowable storms and they were light.
Yeah. So, we we cut it and it was okay for a couple years and now, we're going the other way again.
So we should probably change it back to 25.
>> Yeah. So just let's go back for one second, Jay. This storm,
have you, have we had storms that you
you had to go into your overtime budget for before this one?
Or I mean, I'm asking the question, did we eat the majority of the $15,000
up on this one storm?
>> Oh, not on one storm.
In overtime? Yes. No, it's just the totality of the storms,
you know, since the beginning, you know, since December when we started.
So, we're
>> I think the problem is that when we when we say storms,
I think the public thinks snow.
Yeah. They don't understand that a freezing rain event
or that, you know, an overnight event that maybe was just rained and then froze in the morning, you guys still have to address as a storm.
Yes.
>> Yep. Yeah. But we have, yeah, we have another line item, Adrian, for overtime for public works.
>> That's that's and that's like but that and I'll give you an example.
Jay will back me up on this. They ended up working overtime to get Veterans Park done
in time.
>> Yes. And
we did we did overtime on Bunker Hill Bridge. Right. That's where that stuff goes. We do overtime when there's a windstorm and the trees come down and we gotta go take care of the trees and open up the roads. That's where that overtime comes. What line is that, Jeff? Just the overtime for the public works.
Right. So it's totally separate, Jeff. It's 04:34.
>> And it's fine. That's why I'm asking.
This is why I'm asking the question. I mean, the total overtime
budgeted for the department was $22,000.15000
of it ends up in snowstorm. What I'm trying to grasp in my head, Jay, is we're just talking snow.
>> We're going to, well,
hang on. Get up to go into another.
Share Sherry would have to say where we're at on overtime and snow removal at this point.
But I know
with this with just this past storm, we had 25 and a half plus another five. So we had just over call it thirty two hours for this past storm.
>> Marina did payroll today and she's going to be booking all that information tomorrow.
>> Okay. I'm
sure we're over on our snow budget or overtime on.
Yeah, we were discussing 100 it today.
>> Was doing payroll.
At the time that the spreadsheet was constructed,
we had 3,060
booked into snow removal overtime.
So you had $12,000
left.
Sharing,
just so the community can understand and we can understand, I want to know the overtime that was incurred on that storm
and we should sit there and think about it on a per inch number
and try to understand, okay, that's what per inch is known. Just for the past storm that we had. Just the actual number, Jeff.
Yeah, just the actual number so Give we can
or take $6.
>> Give or take $6, Adrian? Yeah. So Jay, you still have
$6,000.
Yeah.
>> I did thirty two hours at $45 an hour. Are you paying double or single? It's time and a half or is it?
>> Most of it was time and a half this time but we've had we've had several several
storms on double time. You know, we've had it on during the holidays.
Right. And Sundays. So. Yep. Mhmm.
You know,
we can't we can't change when they come in and
you know, you get an ice storm and
sometimes we get those slushy
storms
>> that go all night long. We get it. We get it. We're just trying to understand the math. I actually think you guys did a great job cleaning the roads for this storm. I mean, that's not the issue. The issue is us trying to understand.
Right. Paula's driveway looks great.
Oak Farms Extension.
>> Yep, that looks awesome. You did a great job down there.
Okay,
so
>> Well, we should be able to figure that out, Jeff. I mean, what's a
average
hourly
rate?
>> It's
something that we can sit there and deal with and listen
the reality is Jay honestly I hope it snows between 6AM and 3PM.
That's when I hope it snows.
It
>> sometimes happens, but not always. It doesn't happen a lot, let me tell you. No. All
right. So the snow removal budget right now has not increased, but we should potentially look at that for
overtime issues.
If Sherri can give us that number next week,
that will help us.
>> But does the board agree that we should change the overtime back to 25,000?
>> No, I'm counting on global warming to eliminate this problem.
>> No,
sit there and say, Scott, maybe next week we talk about that line item because I want to see that. I mean, this was a pretty big storm. I mean, Jay, I don't think since you've been here, we've had maybe one other storm that's been that big.
>> Yeah, we had one. We had a couple last year that were long durations and heavy snow.
I mean, Nate,
you're this amount of snow that we had on this storm, you know, you're good at least for one made possibly two of these a winner and the rest of them are all
>> regular problem. Storms. The problem is our
our snow
season has been
running a little longer,
you know, as far as these weird little
gamuts, but also in general, February is our worst worst months. So we're really not going to wait until the end of February. Yeah.
>> You know, and when you guys do go back and talk about overtime,
you should look at the operating side as well. I think we're we're close on that.
You know, you have those storms where we do overtime there, too.
And if we start doing more
road construction when we're doing drainage work,
sometimes you get towards the end of the day and you just need an extra hour or two to wrap something up to make it safe for the weekend. You know, those little things can add up to You're already over on that line, Adam.
We are? Okay.
I knew it was close, but So that brings us to another question.
>> Are we eligible to apply for any FEMA money from the storm?
No, there's no qualifiers for that.
>> And the state the state got FEMA money for it.
On this past storm? Yep.
And I,
>> I don't, I we don't have any qualifiers for that. Okay, know this, I know this, I know the state did because the state put some of their workers on OT,
you know, through the through Sunday, just removing stuff because once they hit FEMA dollars,
they figured we might as well just keep going, you know.
>> Okay,
well I was, I have not been made aware of any FEMA,
qualifiers
that would,
>> for any towns or I don't know, I couldn't answer. And what about the, I mean, the bridge, was any of that repair work redeemable under any of the disaster declarations that were made over the summer with all those storms? No, again, that's, that was, we didn't have the qualifying,
>> don't have the numbers.
Have to reach a certain threshold before you can even think about applying.
>> So we as an individual town have a threshold number?
Yeah. And do we know what that is?
It was a change It's by
>> changed by storm. Then depending on the,
the total dollars,
the feds have to meet it. The state has to meet it. Counties have to meet it. Then the towns,
can
>> I individual
know the state did,
and I know the counties did? So the question is where did we fall in the, you know, and that's something I don't have, I don't have that answer.
So who tracks
that Jay?
For us, who tracks our expenses to know
for that to separate South storm like when you guys are on bridge work. Yeah are we clock, I mean I this was one of the whole issues with going to this.
To going to the clocking system that we have I'm a little frustrated in that the whole reason we wanted electronic
payroll and and electronic
time clocks was so that we could separate
jobs accordingly. So, instead of us randomly trying to have this conversation about how much time you spent at Veterans Park or how much time you spent on Shawty or how much time you spent on the bridge. Yeah, you could put you could pull up a spreadsheet that says, hey, by the way, my guys clocked in for two ninety five hours on the bridge and we clocked in for eighty seven hours a piece over Veterans, right? That's that's that's what I'd like our time clock to be doing. It's not, but somebody somewhere should be tracking this
so that you can tell me how much time you spent on regular maintenance, how much time was on overtime maintenance or repair work, how much time was on drainage because this I mean honestly like if the town rejects this next year I want from you a drainage number to say look this is how much we're spending on drainage every year. Yeah, this is how much how much time we're actually spending on drainage so that the argument cannot be made against it. You know, we can very clearly say this is why we need it, you know. Well, can tell you that I have notes.
>> Keep notes.
Have a log. Is it very accurate?
Sometimes yes, sometimes no.
Actually, I don't have a lot of time to do that because I'm back, You know, I'll do what I can here. I keep a track of bills. I'm keeping my spreadsheets
and I watch the times on
review for payroll and all that, and I make adjustments
and input information where I need to. And then I'm out
working on the roads and I'm part of the crew
as far as the time clock is concerned and its abilities to do what you're speaking of.
Would require guys to
if they had a new job to do a new task in the middle of the day, they'd have to come in, leave the job, come here, punch and punch in, punch out for another slot or if they're signed for the whole day.
And
it would have to be, we'd have to have something with like an iPad or something that we can keep track of that way.
>> Most payroll companies have an app for your phone you really just punch in and out from that during the day. I don't have that set up. Right. I mean, I actually do it, you know, I don't do it anymore now because I've wound down that side of the business, but we used to literally on our phone, I'd have my guys clock in and out to the to the customer's job they were on so that I could actually track hours by job,
you know they all had the APP on their phone they punch on to the next job. And I don't know how you could run a company without that Adrian.
Well.
I would agree with you so.
We. Don't have. The payroll service, we have now does do they have an APP.
No.
They don't.
I
>> know other towns have similar systems that that you speak of. One can think of one town in particular. They call it 311.
It's a it's a program.
The crews have phones, you know, they have town phone, town issued phones,
and they clock in and out on their phones.
The crew leaders have,
iPads
and everything's put into the system.
>> I mean, honestly, of giving guys time issued cell phones,
I'd rather just give them an allotment of, you know, 20 or $30 a month towards their cell phone plan. You know, instead of paying for another plan, another phone, instead of guys having to carry two phones, as long as the Union agreed to it just allow
them to download an APP and then clock in and out and pay towards their plan if it was an issue. You know I don't think the system set up or at least we don't have it set up that way here Adrian. Well, that'll have to be something we look into because I think we're missing, I think we're missing opportunities for grants, for FEMA dollars, for these types of things that could, that could offset some of our expenses as we go, you know. And keeping track of
>> Right. What we actually spend on like just roadside
workers.
Yeah. Or you know,
whatever over overtime.
>> What's seasonal? What's drainage? What's. Right. Yeah. What you know. That's
those are important things for for I know it sounds
like minutiae but it when you get into budget and you start having these conversations minutiae is where residents focus there.
You know they gloss over stuff that we would think is the big issue and they're going to pay attention to the minutiae
So the more information we have, the better. It's data.
>> More data, the more information you get. Don't care from where, I mean, the treasurer's office,
Jay, from public works,
it just makes everything easier.
>> Sheri, I know we're in the middle of budget, but if you can make a mental note that once we get through most of this budget, let's start shopping around for payroll companies. I just asked Marina and she said yes,
>> there is an app.
And I asked her I'm asking her right now if it's set up.
>> Well, and whether or not we can we can code And clock in or clock out. We'll we'll get back to that. And Yeah. Now let's circle back to us. Jay Here's the issue.
It's not available
on
Android
>> anymore. What's
the name of this what's the name of the payroll system?
PrimePay.
Uh-oh. PrimePay.
>> Okay. We will sit there and go back to that. Jay, before we get moving on, is there anything else you'd like to make the board aware of? Thanks for checking on that, Sherry, by the way. You're welcome.
>> Now let's see. We covered operating
the garage budget
building.
Okay. Have you seen that?
Looked at that at all?
Not seeing that. Go ahead. What numbers, Jay?
>> Hang on. I'm switching.
DPW
Garage.
It
is the 309
account
or 3090309.
So
other than the routine
increase,
I shouldn't say routine, nothing's routine.
So
in my building maintenance area,
432.
Is that right, Sherry?
Yes,
432.
>> Okay.
So
another area of the building that I'm trying to
get cleaned up and upgraded is our our oil
lubricants area.
We have a waste oil tank that's non compliant.
So I'd like to purchase a new double wall tank.
I have it in there about $3,400
I don't expect it to go over that 35.
We need to do some electrical
upgrades in this building.
I know we've talked about it before.
I need to
emphasize on one particular area of the building
before we move on to other areas,
but we
approximately,
I don't want say half the building, let's call it a third of the building,
is being powered by
a
they took a three phase area of the building and
I'm not sure of the correct terminology,
but they, you know,
by the use of some kind of transformer,
they
brought the voltage down to supposedly 120, but it's only running around 112.
So we have a low voltage area in the building
that is a compromise to some of our equipment, you know, if you plug something in and things that we run.
But it also,
it's not grounded properly, this area of the building. So if somebody was to
Whatever some accident somehow unplug something,
you know, it could arc,
could you get it's an electrical shock hazard. So we're aware of it. We try not to use those areas,
but
it needs to be fixed
have an estimate.
I have approximate cost of 5,000.
>> That's we have we have we have approved some other repairs.
We have approved some other repairs at some point in the process.
Is that,
that wasn't one of the ones that was on the priority list?
>> You mean as recently?
That's stuff that's already been done? Yeah, in the last year and a half, I want to say. No, the repairs that we had, we did that kitchenette area last year.
That might have been what was,
you know, we had some electrical upgrades, basically some additions
off the panel that was done
when they did the bathrooms,
I guess. So, this is a separate
>> panel? Yeah. Oh yeah. This is, it's not even, they would, they would be bringing, putting in a new panel,
a new sub panel from the, off the main panel
and eliminate
all the wiring on
basically the side of the building where the office is and where the parts room area, it's affecting that area.
The old wiring
in that part
where the parts room is
and some of the electrical outlets in this office area,
the ones that are the old ones not the newer ones,
is being affected
by this low voltage area.
>> I went down there and looked at it and it's
horrible. It's like the oldest wiring I've ever seen in my whole life.
>> Hey Jay, is this just
single phase power you need? You don't need three phase out of this, so it's not like a delta wide transformer?
Correct. It's just a single phase, you're just taking it to three phase and just getting single phase output?
>> They took the three phase and then made it a single phase area, which is here right now, and then it's just
a a mess of wiring that,
in a in a junction box, it's all twisted and got wire ties, and it's it's unbelievable.
>> Cloth wire in there too, I'm imagining? Oh, yes. Yep. Yeah. That probably needs to be upgraded. And single phase transformers are relatively inexpensive.
I don't know what kind of KVA you're looking for, but Well,
>> wouldn't
was
described to me that it wouldn't it wouldn't need a transformer because it's got single phase on the opposite side of the building on the out of the main panel already. You just gotta
to feed this side of the building, just gotta bring a service from off of that panel and put in
another service panel on this side
>> and then and then go from there. Yeah. Haven't been down there to see if there's an eyeliner. So you're saying you got a four eighty volt eyeliner in there and then you kinda come off of that?
>> Yeah. Again, it's a little bit, little bit out of my wheelhouse, but it sounds about right. I
guess if you, if you want to know more, you'd have to come down and see it really.
>> Okay. Yeah. Maybe we can spend, we, maybe we can get together and take a look.
>> So is the $5,000
in the building the building maintenance fund for next
year?
>> That's well, I put it in there
for for that you know, for this fiscal year. I mean, that's included
in the 18,000.
Yes.
>> Yeah.
And I, you know, on the on the standard build and maintenance, you know, just
continuing
pecking away at things in the in the building as we go along. I mean, you
saw Scott, we had,
you know, I did a repair of one of the columns in the building. We got more columns that need to be repaired. This is stuff that we as a crew are doing during our off time in the winter.
You know, as we're doing our services and
we can't be out on the road
doing drainage work, we'll peck away at things here in the building. They've really done a really good job
>> straightening out that building down there. I mean, looks very, very nice,
uncluttered,
neat,
everything's where it belongs.
They have everything
where it belongs,
you know, it's very nice down there now.
>> And that that oil area, the lube area, we also have to get some containment,
55 gallon drum containment pallets.
So there's, you know, there's a
I don't want to call it nickel dime things, but it's, you know, dollars 100, 200 here and there. So that's
my goal is to get that area upgraded.
>> Okay.
Before we let Jay go, is there any other questions anybody has?
Okay. Jay, thank you very much for your time. We appreciate it.
If we have any other questions, we'll sit there and
get them directly to you as we try to finalize the budget items. Okay.
>> Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Good night. Thanks, Jack. Good night, Jay.
>> Since it's 08:41,
were we anticipating
going into executive session?
>> Briefly.
Sherry, just a real quick note, it looks like PrimePay
does have
several apps available on the Android store.
Okay. So
>> maybe we could contact the rep.
It's
we're not looking for just an APP we're looking to be able to code
the work assignments
in some manner.
So that when they they can clock on and off with a code assignment to say I'm going from this job to this job,
so we can build jobs accordingly.
Okay, I
mean you'd still have your overall payroll, but then we divide it all up and say well this what this was maintenance, this was repair, this was. Even if it's just a couple of codes. Okay. If
you could check into that, that'd be great. Yeah.
>> All right. So we're going to move on to Item four, correspondence.
There is none. We're going to move on to Item five, public speak. We'll go back to Diane Choket.
Diane?
I'm all set. All right. Joanne Ebert?
All set as well. Thank you. Okay. Amanda, would you like to say anything?
All set. Thank you. All right.
Sherry, thank you for attending.
You're welcome.
>> All right. Paul, I'm assuming you have control of the meeting? Yep.
Okay.
>> We're now done with public speak. Does someone want to make a motion?
Make a motion to go into executive session.
I second.
Okay.
>> Adrian, just on your motion, I think we should at least put some valid reason.
Just a question.
To possibly replace a system How town
about town administrator?
>> All right, to deal with town administrators
in pending
surgery.
Okay.
>> All right. Just tell me what you want me to say, I'll, you know,
>> but it it is what it is. It's fine.
Paula said all
>> in favor. I. Hang on. Sherry's asking a question. Yes. I was just wondering if it's okay for me to leave. Oh, it's okay for you. All right. Thank you. Thank you, Sherry. Have a good night. Thank you. Thank you, Sherry. You're welcome.
All right. So I'm gonna pause this.